John Thomas Oleson, Jr. 11504 Cantebury Drive Seffner, Florida 33584

tom.oleson@gmail.com Mobile: (813) 334-2072

RESUME OF QUALIFICATIONS

OVERVIEW:

Accomplished senior level software engineer with experience developing enterprise applications in a variety of environments. Development of applications in Java and C++ for desktop, server, and web platforms using IBM, Borland, Microsoft and Oracle on DOS, Windows, Unix and Linux operating systems. Successfully led teams of five to ten people through full life-cycle projects. Excellent analytical, coding and organizational skills combined with clear purpose, focus and vision facilitate efficient completion of tasks and the creation of value.

SKILLS:

Operating Systems/Platforms: Linux, Solaris, AIX, Windows XP/2000/NT/98/95/3.1, OS/2, DOS

Application Environments: Juniper Steel Belted RADIUS, FreeRADIUS, JBoss, Tomcat, Weblogic, IBM WebSphere, J2EE, JFC, MFC, WIN32

Database Servers: Oracle, MySQL, Microsoft SQL Server, IBM DB2, Sybase, Microsoft Access, dBase III, FoxPro, ColdFusion

Development Languages: Java, gcc C/C++, Visual C++, Borland C++, Visual Basic, JavaScript, JSP, HTML, XML, XSL/XSLT, Z80 assembler, 80x86 assembler

Development Environments and Tools: vi, grep, awk, sed, Eclipse, JDK, J2EE, Visual SlickEdit, Visual C++, Borland C++, Visual Basic, IBM VisualAge for Java, Visual Café, Borland JBuilder, Together Control Center, Poseidon for UML, CruiseControl, Jenkins

Other: UML, ODBC/JDBC, AWT, SWT, Velocity, ANT, JUnit, SAX, DOM, JDOM, DOM4J, XML Pull Parser (XPP), Struts, CPPUnit

CERTIFICATIONS:

Brainbench Certifications for C++, C, Java 2, Java 1, RDBMS Concepts and Computer Fundamentals.

EXPERIENCE:

Syniverse Technologies, Tampa, FL (7/2008 – 11/2018) Mobile Data Roaming/WiFi Development

- Advisory/Senior level software engineer responsible for the design and development of C++/Java Linux backend processing applications and Mobile Data Roaming/WiFi C++ plugin components on Juniper's Carrier Level SteelBelted RADIUS (AAA) proxy server on Solaris.
- Principal developer of the Common Messaging Framework (CMF in C++ and Java).
- Principal developer of the metric collection engine for the collection of metrics from high volume formatted input using TCP Sockets and RedHat AMQP.
- Principal developer of MDN routing, Home Roam Blocking, MapBuilder, WiFi RulesEngine and StatEngine as CMF components on the AAA server.
- Work with product management and development team to define application requirements and project scope.
- Object-oriented design and technical specifications for use in software construction.
- Coded new features and performance enhancements for data formatting, data verification, packaging and delivery utilizing Java, C++, XML, POSIX Threads, TCP Sockets, RedHat AMQP, Pro*C, JDBC, OCCI and Oracle on the backend.
- Propagation of improved methods and best practices for code construction, source control, continuous integration builds (using Jenkins) and quality assurance.
- Provide knowledge transfer to increase team efficiency.

Nielsen Media Research, Oldsmar, FL (7/2005 - 6/2008) National IT Division

- Principal senior level developer and team lead responsible for the development of data processing
 and formatted output of All Minute Respondent Level Data (AMRLD) files. AMRLD provides third
 party processors with key household and person by person level information for telecast, program
 viewing, and commercial viewing across broadcast, cable and syndication networks.
- Work with product management to define business rules, application requirements and project scope.
- Use case analysis and modeling using Poseidon for UML.
- Object-oriented design and technical specifications for use in software construction.
- Coded new features and performance enhancements for data formatting, data verification, packaging and delivery utilizing Java, XML, JDBC, Enterprise JavaBeans, Servlets and Velocity on JBOSS, utilizing Redbrick, Sybase and MySQL on the backend.
- Propagation of improved methods and best practices for code construction, source control, continuous integration builds (using CruiseControl) and quality assurance.
- Provide mentoring and knowledge transfer to increase team efficiency.

Datalinx Corporation, (Client Verizon), Tampa, FL (11/2004 - 4/2005) eCOSystem Development Team

- Senior level developer working on the Verizon eCO/eCOT system; a next-generation, work force
 management system enabling Verizon to transform into an eCommerce based Network Factory,
 requiring minimal human intervention throughout its business processes by enhancing the efficiency
 of technicians and their supervisors working in the Central Office and Operations Centers.
- Work with management to define business rules, application requirements and project scope.
- Object-oriented design and technical specifications for use in software construction.
- Coded network accessible performance enhancements for improved work order pagination and viewing and enhanced logging, utilizing Enterprise JavaBeans, Servlets, JSP, XML, HTML, XSL/XSLT, CSS, JavaScript and JDBC providing support for DB2 on the backend.
- Propagation of improved methods and best practices for code construction, source control, builds and quality assurance.
- Provide mentoring and knowledge transfer to increase team efficiency.

Skyway Software, Inc., Tampa, FL (11/2001 – 10/2004) Engineering

- One of four architects responsible for the design and development of our Enterprise level business process management application builder.
- Architect of code generation, runtime process logic and deployment functionality.
- Work with business analysts, product management and marketing to define business rules, application requirements and project scope.
- Use case analysis and modeling using Visio, Together Control Center and UML.
- Object-oriented design and technical specifications for use in software construction.
- Coded new features and enhancements for code generation, runtime processes, deployment and
 execution utilizing Enterprise JavaBeans, Servlets, Velocity, XPP, XML, HTML, JMS, and JDBC on
 JBOSS and Weblogic providing support for Oracle, MySQL, Microsoft SQL Server and DB2 on the
 backend.
- Coded XML and database metadata processing used to feed code generation, deployment and runtime layers.
- Introduced improved methods and best practices for code construction, source control, builds and quality assurance.
- Organized teams and facilitated improvements to our development process.
- Provided mentoring and knowledge transfer to increase team efficiency.

Sapphire Technologies (Client AT&T), Tampa, FL (7/2001 - 10/2001)

- Senior level developer working on a SCORM 1.1 compliant Learning Management System (LMS) for use in the delivery of on-line training to AT&T, AT&T Partners, AT&T Associates and customers.
- Work with management to define business rules, application requirements and project scope.
 Modeling using Together Control Center and UML.
- Object-oriented design and technical specifications for use in software construction.
- Coded new network accessible features utilizing Enterprise JavaBeans, Servlets, JSP, XML, HTML, CSS, Struts, JavaScript, XYZ Find and JDBC providing support for Oracle on the backend.
- Introduced improved methods and best practices for code construction, source control, builds and quality assurance.
- Provide mentoring and knowledge transfer to increase team efficiency.

TRADEX and Ariba, Inc., Tampa, FL (1999 – 2001) Ariba Marketplace Development

- Team lead in four major releases of our B2B Marketplace software running on Windows NT and Solaris. Organized teams and facilitated improvements to our development process.
- Work with business analysts, product management, project management and marketing to define business rules, application requirements and project scope.
- Use case analysis and modeling using Structure Builder, Together Control Center and UML.
- Object-oriented design and technical specifications for use in software construction.
- Coded new features utilizing Enterprise JavaBeans, Servlets, Applets, JSP, XML, HTML, JMS, Sockets and JDBC providing support for Oracle, Sybase, Microsoft SQL Server and DB2 on the backend. Coded business logic for XML/cXML and EJB integration of Ariba Marketplace with Ariba Dynamic Trade (online auctions), Ariba Buyer and Ariba Commerce Services Network (ACSN).
- Introduced improved methods and best practices for code construction, source control, builds and quality assurance.
- Provided mentoring and knowledge transfer to increase team efficiency.

IBM, Tampa, FL (1998 – 1999) Web Hosting Development – Infrastructure & Database Support

- Team lead for IBM responsible for the design and development of eBusiness client/server database management applications running on Windows NT and AIX.
- Work with end-users and project management to define goals, requirements and project scope.
- Object-oriented design and technical specifications for use in software construction.
- Coded implementation of database management systems for order fulfillment and server farm configuration utilizing IBM VisualAge for Java, IBM DB2 and Lotus Domino.

- Designed and coded a new n-tier client/server application framework based on business objects with object-relational mapping, a thin-client using RMI and server components utilizing JDBC for access to a DB/2 database.
- Coded implementation of a network accessible batch load facility for server farm configuration data using HTML, a client applet and RMI.
- Organized teams and facilitated improvements to our development process.
- Provided mentoring and knowledge transfer to increase team efficiency.

UTILITY PARTNERS, INC., Tampa, FL (1998) Product Development - MobileField Systems

- Software Engineer for the development of custom versions of a RF, LAN and Circuit Switched Cellular communications layer (APPCOM) using Visual C++ providing services to Visual Basic applications running on mobile Windows 3.1/95 work-slate computers.
- Object-oriented design and technical specifications for use in software construction.
- Coded processing and event handling logic for the APPCOM driver.
- Provided mentoring and knowledge transfer to increase team efficiency.

JOHN H. HARLAND, Tampa, FL (1997 - 1998) Financial Marketing Division - Product Development - Householding Systems

- Team lead for Harland in the development of a Java based tool for the creation and maintenance of mainframe parameters.
- Lead developer responsible for the maintenance of proprietary financial marketing database applications written in the C language using C Set for OS/2 and Visual C++ for Windows NT.
- Object-oriented design and technical specifications for use in software construction.
- Coded user interface components and parameter parser logic for display, modification and persistence of mainframe parameter files.
- Provided mentoring and knowledge transfer to increase team efficiency.
- Facilitated improvements to our development process.

UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH FLORIDA, Tampa, FL (1986 - 1997) Office of Research/Parking Services Department

- Sr. Computer Programmer/Analyst responsible for development of office automation projects first in Parking Services and then the Office of Research.
- Local Area Network Administrator for both Parking Services and the Office of Research (NetWare, Windows NT Server, Exchange Server).
- Setup, installation and configuration of servers, workstations and hardware supporting over eighty users.
- Design and technical specifications for use in software construction.
- Design and implementation of a citation system on hand-held touch screen computers for use by parking patrol officers. Software was developed in a DOS environment using Borland C++ and the hand-held BIOS.
- Design and implementation of a vehicle registration, decal sales and fines collection system providing point-of-sale, optical mark reader data entry and integration to the hand-held citation system running on DOS and developed using Borland C++.
- Design and code implementation of relational database components utilizing the C programming language and the CodeBase library (an RDBMS library written in C).
- Design and code implementation of a dial-up communications system featuring file transfers, database access, e-mail and an embedded C language interpreter.
- Design and code implementation of a research administration application for grants and proposals written in Microsoft Access running on Windows 95/NT.
- Design and code implementation of the Office of Research web site providing database access via ColdFusion running on Windows NT.
- Supervision of department's computer support specialists.
- Provide operational training on automated systems.

COMPUTER WORKS OF FLORIDA, Tampa, FL (1985) Service Department

 Software Support Technician providing customer support for the installation and use of operating system and applications software.

UNITED STATES NAVY, Brunswick, ME (1981 - 1985)

Patrol Squadron Eleven, AW2, Second Class Petty Officer (E-5)

- Aviation anti-submarine warfare operator flying on P3C Orion long-range patrol aircraft.
- Operation of non-acoustic sensors and on-board computers for the purpose of localizing and tracking submarines and surface ships. Qualified in multiple areas utilizing classified information.
- Over 1,000 hours of flight time.

STRENGTHS:

Ability to tactfully and effectively coordinate with a wide range of people on all levels... to make reasonable and timely decisions... mastering new challenges as they arise. Analytical, thorough and innovative. A proven organizer who knows the value of planning and follow-through on work in progress. Strong C/C++, RDBMS and Java programming skills.

EDUCATION:

Microsoft Course 540 - Supporting Microsoft Windows 95 (1996)

Microsoft Course 505 - Supporting Microsoft Windows NT 3.51 (1996)

Microsoft Course 659 - Supporting Microsoft Windows NT Server (1996)

Microsoft Course 472 - Internetworking Microsoft TCP/IP on Windows NT 3.51 (1996)

Microsoft Course 730 - Fundamentals of Microsoft Exchange Server (1996)

Client/Server Computing Course (1994)

TCP/IP Internetworking Course (1994)

Advanced Airborne Electronic Warfare School (1983)

Airborne Electronic Warfare School (1983)

Non-Acoustic ASW Flight School (1982)

Antisubmarine Warfare School (1982)

Aviation Fundamentals School (1981)

Naval Aircrew Candidate School (1981)

Bayshore Methodist High School, Tampa, FL (1980)

SALARY:

NEGOTIABLE